YWCA of the U.S.A. Records. Record Group 6. Program: Series V. Program Subjects
Sophia Smith Collection
YWCA of the U.S.A. Records. Record Group 06. Program: Series V. Program Subjects
1870-2002
Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A.
324_rg6_s5
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
This series documents the National Association's work related to Camping and Outdoor Recreation; Health and Recreation; Music; Pageantry and Drama; and Religion. Forms part of the YWCA of the U.S.A. Records. Record Group 6. Program.
NOTE: For the most part, the Microfilmed Records and the Original Format Records do not duplicate each other and both should be consulted. This description covers materials in both formats. See the Contents List for a folder-level inventory of the Original Format Records. See the Microfilmed Records Reel Lists for a detailed inventory of the microfilm.
Forms part of the YWCA of the U.S.A. Records--Record Group 6. Program.
This Series is divided into five Subseries:
A. CAMPING AND OUTDOOR RECREATION
B. HEALTH AND RECREATION
C. MUSIC
D. PAGEANTRY AND DRAMA
E. RELIGION
SUBSERIES A. CAMPING AND OUTDOOR RECREATION
Historical Note
Many young women had their first exposure to the YWCA through Summer Camps run by Community Associations all over the United States. Though camps were primarily the province of Community Associations, the National Staff served as consultants on the educational philosophy of camping and outdoor recreation and produced publications and other program materials for use at camps and in recreational programs. Staff in the Business Department also consulted with locals on administrative and property management issues.
At times during its history, the National Association owned some camp properties and major summer conferences and councils took place at various regional camps, such as Camp Maqua in Poland, Maine and Camp Okoboji in Milford, Iowa.
The National Association hired specialist staff to consult on camping for two rather brief periods, from 1925 to 1932, and 1965 to 1969. The latter period coincided with general Association concern over declining membership among the young, a growing environmental movement, and increased interest in outdoor recreation and conservation. During this period the YWCA sponsored two national conferences on Outdoor Recreation and Conservation. An associated Y-Teen Pilot Work Camp in which campers built a trail in the Teton National Forest became the subject of a film and garnered quite a bit of press coverage.
Administrative History
1925-31 Camps in Education and Research
1932 Director of Camps Maqua and Okoboji under Business Committee
1959 Consultant, Camping Program in Leadership Services
1965 Consultant, Camping in Community Division
1966 Consultant, Camping and Program with Children Under 12 in Community Division
1967 Consultant, Camping, Outdoor Recreation, and Conservation in Community Division
1968 Consultant, Camping and Outdoor Recreation in Community Division
1969 Consultant, Special Programs and Camping in Community Division
Scope and Content
The Camping and Outdoor Recreation records consist of general historical materials; brochures and general information about some of the camps used for national conferences and councils; minutes and reports of national and regional camp committees and commissions from the 1910s and 1920s; correspondence, Conference and Program files primarily from the 1960s; publications; reference materials; and miscellaneous scrapbooks and memorabilia. Publications cover topics such as administration and educational philosophy of camping, nature study, and outdoor activities.
Microfilmed Records, 1906-70 only
[see Microfilmed Records Reel List]
Microfilmed records include minutes and reports of various Camp committees and commissions, 1912-27; general information files on the camps Altamont, Canadohta, Makonikey, Maqua, Nepahwhin, Okoboji, and others; and files on the two national recreation and conservation conferences and the film "Aim, Achieve, Action" made at the Y-Teen Pilot Work Camp in 1966. The records do not contain a copy of the film itself. They can be found on the Microfilm in:
Minutes and Reports
Camp Department
Subject Files
Arts, Motion Pictures [information about Y-Teen Pilot Work Camp film]
Camps
Conference
Original Format Records, 1912-71, n.d., 3 linear feet
[see Original Format Records folder list]
In addition to the Minutes and Reports (which were not discarded after filming), the Original Format Records contain 1960s working files of the Camping and Outdoor Recreation Consultant that were transferred to the National Board Archives after microfilming was complete. They include a sample of her consulting work with individual camps and her files on the national conferences and Y-Teen Pilot Work Camp. The Miscellaneous materials include an assortment of scrapbooks, memorabilia, and records of individual camps run by Community Associations.
The Original Format Records are arranged as follows:
General and history
Minutes and Reports
Correspondence
Conferences
Programs
Publications
Reference materials
Miscellaneous
Related Materials
Elsewhere in this Series
The YWCA often had specialist staff for indoor (vs. outdoor) recreation. Similar materials about the philosophy of recreation and play are in Subseries B. Health and Recreation.
Elsewhere in this Record Group
The AssociationMonthly/Womans Press/YWCA Magazine in SERIES VI. PUBLICATIONS is an excellent source for most topics. It tended to have a special Camp issue each summer.
There are many camp-related records in Subseries D. Teenage and Younger Girls Program in SERIES IV. CONSTITUENT GROUPS
See also files about Summer Conferences, in SERIES IV. CONSTITUENT GROUPS
There are reports on and discussion of camps in Education and Research minutes in SERIES I. DEPARTMENT, STAFF, AND COMITTEES.
In other Record Groups
Data and Statistics regularly collected and compiled information on Community Association Camp programs. These are in SERIES IV of RECORD GROUP 3. NATIONAL ADMINISTRATIVE OFFICE.
Files on Camp properties owned by the National Association are in SERIES II of RECORD GROUP 3. NATIONAL ADMINISTRATIVE OFFICE.
Lillian Rifken Blumenfeld's memories of Camp Winola are in SERIES V. BIOGRAPHICAL FILES in RECORD GROUP 1. GENERAL AND HISTORY.
RECORD GROUP 9. PHOTOGRAPHS includes a smattering of camp photographs and an especially rich set of files on the Y-Teen Pilot Work Camp.
Personal Papers
The Sophia Smith Collection holds personal papers of a few YWCA women who ran Camp programs, particularly overseas. They include: Frances Ticknor and Polly Feustal.
SUBSERIES B. HEALTH AND RECREATION
Historical Note
The YWCA of the U.S.A. defined health, which it considered "the right of every individual" as physical, mental, and social well-being. Its program of "positive health" a term coined by its first Secretary for Health, Dr. Anna L. Brown encompassed not only activities related to physical health, such as health examinations, health education, and physical recreation opportunities; but also the opportunities Community YWCAs provided for creative expression, cultural enrichment, rest and relaxation, social interaction, and other forms of personal fulfillment and spiritual growth.
Such a wide-ranging assortment of activities, though a core concern of the YWCA, were never the province of a single department. While the National Association had staff, usually medical doctors, for overseeing health education, responsibility for all of the other aspects included in the concept of "positive health," was spread over many staff members in various departments.
The first Health Secretary, Anna Brown, had been General Secretary of the predecessor organization to the YWCA of the U.S.A. known as the International Board. Brown was "called" to national leadership for physical education and hygiene by the National Association's first President, Grace Dodge. An early student of psychology, Brown appreciated the importance of psychological as well as physical and spiritual health and established a program emphasizing normal growth for the whole individual, as a defense against physical, mental, and moral ills. Her program included hygiene, physical education, nutrition, sex education, and a campaign promoting "health shoes," a topic Brown approached with particular zeal. "Under [her] leadership…a program of health was evolved which radically differed from all others. For the first time health was seen as freedom, vital force, power, energy and not a lack of it. Health was a bank account for life's possibilities, not the commonly held idea which limits it to attacking handicaps and diseases." (typescript "History" author unknown, circa 1930) Dr. Brown pioneered the concept of "health examinations" or check ups, and incorporated them into YWCA program as part of physical education classes.
In its report to Convention in 1913, the Commission on Social Morality from the Christian Standpoint recommended establishment of a program "in the social training of women and girls with particular reference to sex education." Four lecturers were carefully chosen for a pilot program to speak on the subject to young women college and university students. Lecturers stressed "knowledge of normal sex life" and addressed their audiences with unusual frankness.
As was the case in many other areas of YWCA Program, World War I brought a huge expansion in the physical education and recreation work. Some of the core activities provided in Industrial Service Centers and Community Associations through the war years, were physical and recreational activities to relieve stress and keep workers fit.
The YWCA organized a Bureau of 150 women physicians to give sex education lectures to young women in communities surrounding military camps and industrial plants. Because of its experience in this area, the U.S. Government asked the YWCA to assist its Social Hygiene Division in setting up a similar program. The Bureau of Social Education, established at the end of the war in 1919, continued the work through the reconstruction period through lectures, publications, charts, films, etc.
As a result of this work, the YWCA organized the first International Conference of Women Physicians in 1919. Attendees came from 32 countries for six weeks to focus on women's health issues, including such topics as general problems of health, industrial health, children's health, moral codes and personality, adaptation of the individual to life, and conservation of the health of women in marriage.
Women's health issues became one of the Convention emphases in 1920 with a resolution stating that poor physical health was one of the greatest barriers to social and economic progress for women. The YWCA pledged to change prevailing notions of women's physical incapacity.
In response to the deepening economic Depression, the 1930 Convention passed a resolution giving renewed emphasis to a program of play and recreation as an antidote to despair. Yet, the staff cuts necessitated by the Depression resulted in a much-reduced health and recreation program.
Though physical recreation remained a bread-and-butter activity at Community YWCAs, and perhaps the area most associated with the YWCA in the public mind, the major reduction in Program staff that began in the 1930s meant that the national effort languished. What had been a national staff of 23 in 1920 had been reduced to a single consultant by 1954. The Health, Physical Education and Recreation Consultant facilitated establishment of new programs in the 1950s, such as judo and family recreational activities, including canoe and boat handling and fly fishing.
In the late 1980s the National Association received funding for Teen Sexuality Education and Pregnancy Prevention Programs [see Teenage and Younger Girls Program in SERIES IV. of this Record Group.]
In the 1980s and 1990s, the National Association sought U.S. Government Grants and corporate sponsorship for women's health programs. One was the ENCORE (Encouragement, Normalcy, Counseling, Opportunity, Reaching out, Energies Revived) post-mastectomy and exercise program for women with breast cancer. Originally developed at the Princeton YWCA, the National Association obtained Rippel Foundation funding for a pilot program in thirty Community Associations in 1974. ENCORE was adopted as an official national program two years later.
The National Association began a collaboration with the U.S. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) in 1992 to enhance the effectiveness of the CDC's National Breast and Cervical Cancer Early Detection Program, known as "Project Awareness." Beginning in 1993, CDC and the YWCA developed a program to foster collaborative relationships between Community YWCAs and state health departments to provide education and screening to underserved women. In addition to creating educational materials, the collaboration included two demonstration projects: the Maryland Partnership and the Lesbian Demonstration Project to test methods and techniques for effective collaboration.
Through this program, the YWCA expanded the traditional ENCORE post-mastectomy program to include breast and cervical cancer education, and screening and early detection services. The revised version is known as ENCOREplus.
Oct 1993 Avon launched a three-year cause-related marketing initiative "Avon's Breast Cancer Awareness Crusade" designed to generate funds to support community-based activities that promote access to screening and early detection services especially for medically underserved women. ENCOREplus was one of two programs chosen to receive funds from the initiative.
The National Association established an Office of Women's Health Initiatives in 1994 to oversee these various initiatives. Initially part of the Executive Office, the staff joined the Office of Health Promotion and Sports Advocacy in the Division of Advocacy and Research in 1995.
In the mid-1990s with funds from Nike Products, Inc., the National Association developed the YWCA/Nike Sports and Fitness Project, to provide grants to Community YWCAs for basketball, volleyball, and "New Face of Fitness" fitness training programs. The team sports programs stressed the educational and social benefits of discipline and team work as well as physical benefits of participation in sports.
Given the YWCA's longstanding advocacy on behalf of working women, some Community Associations objected when the National Association accepted funding from Nike, a corporation somewhat notorious for its unfair labor practices overseas. Their concerns prompted creation of a Corporate Partnership Policy in 1998. [see RECORD GROUP 3. NATIONAL ADMINISTRATIVE OFFICE]
Administrative History
1907-10 Anna Brown, Home Department
1910-18 Anna Brown, City Committee in Department of Method
1918-19 Bureau of Social Morality in War Work Council; and Recreation Work, Town and Country in Department of Method
1919 Social Education in War Work Staff, and Recreation Work in Department of Research and Method
1920-22 Social Education, Health, Recreation, Athletics, and Physical Education in Research and Method; Recreation in Department of Field Work; and Physical Education in Post-Continuation Committee
1923 Social Education in Education and Research
1925-27 Health Education in Education and Research
1928-31 Health Education in Field Division
1932-35 Health Education in National Services Division; Creative Arts in Laboratory Division
1935-39 Health Education in National Services Division
1940-47 Health Education in Community Division
1948-49 Bureau of Immigration and the Foreign-Born
fall 1935 Nationality Community Interests in Program and Research under Laboratory Division
1936 International Interests (or Nationality Community Interests) in Program, and Research under Laboratory Division
1939 Refugees in Program and Research under Laboratory Division
1940-43 Nationality Community Interests in Community Division
1944 Health Education and Camping in Community Division and regional staff in Health Education
1950-51 Health Education in Training Services
1952 Membership Resources in Leadership Services
1959 Consultant, Health, Physical Education, and Recreation, in Leadership Services
1960 -71 Consultant, Health, Physical Education, and Recreation in Community Division
1971-76 Health and Environment in Program Policy and Development
1976-83 Health, Physical Education and Recreation in Program Unit (sometimes includes ENCORE)
1984-87 Health, Physical Education and Recreation in Program Services Division
1987-91 Health, Physical Education and Recreation; and Teen Pregnancy Prevention in Program Services Division
1992-94 Health Promotion and Sports in Advocacy and Research
1994 Health Promotion and Sports in Advocacy and Research; and Office of Women's Health Initiatives in Executive Office
1995- Health Promotion and Sports and Office of Women's Health Initiatives in Advocacy and Research
Scope and Content
The records in this series document national efforts related to health, health education, sports, exercise, and recreation. Included are minutes, mailings, reports, studies, correspondence, surveys, and publications. These tend to be somewhat scattered items brought together for the Central Subject File, rather than comprehensive records of health and recreation activities. Prior to establishment of the Office of Health Promotion and Sports Advocacy in 1992, national staff responsible for health and recreation were a part of other departments of the YWCA. See Related Materials below for locations of additional records. The post-1992 records give a somewhat more comprehensive picture of national staff activities related to health and recreation.
Major topics include physical health, mental health, sex education, marriage and family life education (consisting of relationships education, sex education, and balancing work and family); menopause; "health" shoes; nutrition; exercise and sport; and various forms of indoor recreation, such as arts, crafts, dancing, and parties). Materials about outdoor recreation can be found in Subseries A. Camping and Outdoor Recreation.
Among the records are the publications produced out of the groundbreaking International Conference of Women Physicians hosted by the YWCA in 1919.
Programs and Projects files include a modest amount of materials from the early 1920s when the work was supported with World War I continuation funds and a substantial body of records of 1990s cancer-related and sports and fitness programs.
The publications are especially extensive and diverse. They deal with such topics as the administration of health programs; feet and shoes; menopause; sex education; marriage and family life (including jobs and marriage); the development, needs and interests of young girls and adolescents; arts; crafts; parties; and games.
Microfilmed Records, 1890-1970
[see Microfilmed Records Reel List]
The Health and Recreation records on the microfilm include general historical information; conference and training materials; publications, including the Health Education Bulletin (1935-44); reference files; and records of the work of the Bureau of Social Education.
Health and Recreation records can be found on the microfilm under:
Minutes and Reports
Health Education Study
Health Education Committee
Subject Files
Arts
Health
Health Education
World War I, Social Morality, International Conference of Women Physicians
Original Format Records, 1890-2002, n.d., (bulk 1919-36, 1993-99), 15 linear feet
[see Original Format Records Folder List]
The Original Format Records contain substantial post-microfilm materials which are primarily women's health and recreation Programs and Projects files from the 1990s. the Minutes and Reports and roughly half of the records microfilmed under "Health" (reel 96, microdexes 2 through 6) were not discarded after filming and are available in original format. The Womans Press published an array of hardcover books on various health and recreation topics, many of which were not included in the microfilm.
The Original Format Records are organized as follows:
General and history includes historical essays; reports; general and policy statements; bibliographies; and radio scripts about the YWCA health program.
Committees, Commissions, Offices contains minutes, reports, mailings, and some correspondence and memoranda produced by the major YWCA Committees and Commissions, and the staff and offices responsible for the health program.
Conferences and Workshops, is divided into internal YWCA events and national and international "non-YWCA" events in which YWCA health staff participated. Included are reports and planning materials as well as a complete set of publications from the 1919 International Conference of Women Physicians (hosted by the YWCA).
Programs and Projects files are primarily records of women's health programs, such as ENCORE and ENCOREplus, and recreation programs, such as YWCA/Nike basketball, volleyball, and New Face of Fitness programs in the 1990s.
The Publications are arranged in two broad categories: Health (which includes General, Administration, Marriage and Family Life Education, Mental Health, and Sex Education) and Recreation (which includes General, Arts and Crafts, Dance, and Parties and Games). General serials are filed at the end of the section.
Reference Materials consists primarily of general articles and pamphlets on marriage and family life, recreation, adolescent development and sex education.
Training includes texts of "Social Morality" lectures from 1915 and 1917, a few health training materials from the 1990s, and some other miscellaneous items.
Related Materials
Elsewhere in this Series
Subseries A. Camping and Outdoor Recreation had related records about recreational activities outdoors and the philosophy of play and recreation.
Subseries D. Pageantry and Drama contains a number of scripts related to various health issues.
Later records related to creative arts and crafts can be found in Subseries C. Music Program, as the creative arts aspect of "recreation" became the responsibility of Music Secretary in 1950s.
Elsewhere in this Record Group
Health secretaries were based in the Department of Method and Division of Education and Research up to 1928, their work is described in the Minutes and Reports in SERIES I. DEPARTMENT, STAFF, AND COMMITTEES.
SERIES III. PUBLIC ADVOCACY has files on a variety of health-related topics including health care, health insurance; and domestic violence as a public health issue.
YWCA programs paid particular attention to health education for teens and the psychology of adolescents. Records of these activities can be found in SERIES IV. CONSTITUENT GROUPS, Subseries D. Teenage and Younger Girls Program. There are also records of teen pregnancy prevention and other teen programs related to health, such as Peer Approach Counseling by Teens (PACT).
SERIES VII. WAR WORK AND DEFENSE SERVICES contains records about recreational activities for servicemen, industrial war workers, and the general membership. The World War I Subseries includes records of the Bureau of Social Education and its sex and health education work. The World War II Subseries also has sex education items as well as publications written for women about the potential psychological problems of returning soldiers.
In other Record Groups